<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <title>Alex Payne</title>
 <link href="https://al3x.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://al3x.net/"/>
 <updated>2017-11-15T02:51:08-08:00</updated>
 <id>http://al3x.net/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Alex Payne</name>
   <email>al3x@al3x.net</email>
 </author>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Three Days in San Francisco in 2015</title>
   <link href="https://al3x.net/2017/05/11/three-days-in-san-francisco-in-2015.html"/>
   <updated>2017-05-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://al3x.net/2017/05/11/three-days-in-san-francisco-in-2015</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;three-days-in-san-francisco-in-2015&quot;&gt;Three Days in San Francisco in 2015&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wednesday&quot;&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A homeless man, screaming. The taxi driver and I can hear him from down the block as the cab comes in for a stop. Looking out the window at the screaming man, the driver chuckles as I traverse payment screens. “He’s angry about something,” the driver says, smiling. I haul my suitcase into a Scandinavian chain brewpub down the block from where the screaming man is attempting to stand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My evening is spent with people I’ve known for years. Three of them I’ve barely met in person before. That hasn’t kept us from maintaining windows into each other’s lives as we’ve changed jobs, moved around, started and ended relationships. The photos from my life that I won’t share with just anyone, I share with these people. I’ve come straight from the airport so I don’t miss even a few minutes of their company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend’s wife is a therapist. Her colleagues are trying to figure out how technology fits into their practices. Can they, as therapists, help programmers in particular? Is a person who works in technology fundamentally different from any other patient? I learn that the therapists of San Francisco don’t know how technology will change what they do, but they know it will, somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our night ends in a taqueria on an untended block of Market Street. The other customers are not like us, or we’re not like them, the differences conspicuous but only silently addressed through the positioning of our bodies within the narrow, crowded space in front of the counter. One customer paces intensely, mobile phone to his ear. While we wait for our food, at least two people walk in, get no more than a few paces past the door, and turn back. They forgot their orders, or they forgot how to order, or they forgot that they couldn’t pay. The taqueria closes up as we leave, hours before the app that pointed me there claimed it would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had already checked into my hotel room before I got dressed this morning, 637 miles away. I don’t talk to anyone at the front desk, leaving me feeling like an intruder as I roll my suitcase into the elevator and down a hall. My phone tells me the room number, and it is also my room key. I wave it near the lock and the two devices eventually  agree to let me in after a seemingly fraught negotiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A former employer put me up in this hotel the first time I visited the city. It’s still where I stay when I come back. My San Francisco radiates outwards from this hotel. The decor and branding is overdone. On weekends the lobby dins with generic brand dance music, reminding me of living on 3rd Street, the triumphant cries of 2 AM nightclub heroines and heroes soaring over fading bass thumps into the single window of my studio apartment. A place comfortingly familiar even in its irritations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thursday&quot;&gt;Thursday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sleep in just a few too many minutes to walk the completely reasonable walk to the water, so I pay for a taxi in dollars and guilt. My friend arrives by ferry, which is, right, why they call it the Ferry Building. When we try to buy vegan donuts the vendor’s card reader doesn’t work; my friend pays cash. We buy chai from a cart, walk and talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few minutes later I’m sweating. I’d forgotten the humidity that sets in after the fog pours down the hills. My friend tells me about his newborn, his house on the other side of the Bay in a neighborhood where people still know their neighbors. Our conversation is interrupted by jackhammer blasts on every block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People I used to work with invested in a coffee shop that’s now always full. When I first came here, the coffee shop was two benches and a stand. Now it’s two massive wood-clad stories, as if the benches and stand joined forces and swelled steroidally into a warehouse. The roasting machine is always going, reminding the olfactory that roasting coffee beans don’t smell quite like coffee but do smell a little bit like burnt shit. You have to wait for a startup pitch to end before you can sit down here. I’m being pitched a startup too, but we stand. It turns out that the two founders and I know all the same people; of course we do, that’s how this works. I’m surprised at the sweetness of what they’re building. I drop my guard and help brainstorm revenue models. The sweet ones are rare and I want them to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My lunch meeting is at a vegetarian Thai restaurant in that unfeasibly bland part of town where the dense human suffering of the Tenderloin gives way to wide boulevards of auto dealerships that have no business being in the city center. Another set of founders – younger, still white and male – walk me through what they’ve built, and I like it. I wasn’t expecting to like much today. The founders are ambitious but practical economics majors who taught themselves to code. We poke at a laptop in the otherwise empty restaurant. Just two people can do so much more now than they could just a few years ago. People say that when they’re selling something but sometimes you get to see that it’s really true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I buy eyedrops from a pharmacy. I take a taxi to a possible future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up the street from where I used to work is a lab that’s an extension of another lab. The lab’s current funding is improbable, its future funding uncertain. Inside, I’m shown things that – no, it’s not magic, because you can see how it works, but still. They’ve made a room into a computer program and vice versa. You can walk up to the room-code and read it. I’m trying so hard to come up with questions because I know that in a few minutes I’ll have to leave and I might never see anything like this again. I just want to stand there with my mouth open and gawp until they make me go home. The few people in this lab have made something so humane and approachable that it’s hard to imagine it ever becoming part of the vulgar world outside. Like the pause before closing a favorite childhood storybook, I don’t want to leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another person I’ve known of for years online but have never met in person has invited me to a hipster Jewish deli in a neighborhood that is every day less Mexican. Some of us believe so much in what technology can do for people that we get scared and angry when we see it going wrong. We each can’t say enough, purge enough, in the presence of another person who feels the same. It’s a roasted mushroom reuben confessional. The waitress, bearing a freshly bandaged tattoo, rightfully glares at us when our voices rise with concerned enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I go to the water again, this time to the east. At what looks like a yacht club that someone long ago gave up on, I reconnect with people I used to work with and meet the people they used to work with. We’re all here to put faces to names on a list of people we hope we’ll make some money with. I joke with a venture capitalist about the food. She almost steals a french fry from a tray carried by a passing server before realizing it wasn’t for our group. The sun starts to go down, the humidity is gone, everyone and the french fries gets cold, apps summon cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;friday&quot;&gt;Friday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The VC’s assistant did such a good job picking a desirable place for our breakfast meeting that we can’t get a table for all the weekday brunch-goers. We talk in a deserted generic deli nearby instead. There are a few investors whose portfolios I respect, to the slim extent that it’s reasonable and right to respect a set of informed bets on the projected profits of other people’s labor. I learn over breakfast that the people who put money into the hands of VCs are best treated as individuals and not a herd. The VC sounds wistful for a time when he worked alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neighborhood I first lived in when I arrived in San Francisco has become even more precious than it used to be. It is a cartoon place now. The core of the neighborhood is the sort of intentionally-planned public space that somehow feels less humane for all the effort. Twentysomethings in a fitness program run in circles in front of a jutting, angular sign-sculpture that maybe claims its surrounding area for open air theater, sometimes? A friend tells me that the temple-like structure in the center of the planned space will be ignited at Burning Man, that the names scrawled in marker on its laser-cut pale wood frame are the names of the dead, and that their memories will symbolically go up in smoke out there in the desert. Then he tells me about his new startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few blocks over, I meet another friend for lunch. My friend proposes a bottle of wine because he’s off to a music festival that afternoon so fuck it. He’s been traveling and has gone shaggy, more than a bit Val Kilmer. Tight lines extending from our eyes now, gray hairs creeping in. We’ve had a similar past few years. Now he’s trying to build something again, but knows better what that costs, so cautiously, cautiously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The smell of trash wafts over the restaurant’s patio, masking the rosé, and I want to go home.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
   <author>
     <name>Alex Payne</name>
     <uri>https://al3x.net/about.html</uri>
   </author>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What Pro Computing Could Be</title>
   <link href="https://al3x.net/2016/10/31/pro-computing.html"/>
   <updated>2016-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://al3x.net/2016/10/31/pro-computing</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-pro-computing-could-be&quot;&gt;What Pro Computing Could Be&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the announcement late last week of revised MacBook Pro models it has become clear that a certain type of person &lt;a href=&quot;http://mjtsai.com/blog/2016/10/27/new-macbook-pros-and-the-state-of-the-mac/&quot;&gt;is not happy&lt;/a&gt; with the first major revision to Apple’s flagship portable computer in some years. Those complaints have sparked broader speculation amongst the twittering classes as to whether Apple is still a company that makes computing devices for “pros”: software developers, graphic designers, video editors, 3D modelers, audio engineers, data scientists, and others whose livelihoods depend on fast machines with plenty of memory and myriad ways of moving data in, out, and around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have one friend in particular who I talk about these sorts of tech product announcements with. Last Thursday’s Apple event was just the latest in our long chain of messages on the general topic of pro computing. It’s a subject we have strong feelings about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conversation over two years ago, we converged on an assumption: Apple and Microsoft will taper off their investments in pro hardware and software while they chase bigger, easier money in the consumer and enterprise spaces. History being known to repeat itself, we saw a moment on the horizon not unlike the one in which NeXT and Be emerged. We figured there were some instructive lessons from the histories of those upstarts. We wondered if the right team could move pro computing forward today, and by measures beyond small increments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend and I then started sketching a wholesale rethinking of professional computing in the form of an integrated hardware and software platform. We quickly became obsessed. We tore through journal articles and whitepapers on topics like heterogenous computing. My friend started designing a motherboard. We sourced components. We wrote the beginnings of an operating system (for the trainspotters: in x86_64 assembly and Rust). We worked on the system’s concepts up and down the stack, from UI to networking to a new toolchain. We tried to get into the heads of pro users while throwing out preconceptions of how an OS works and functions. It was probably the most interesting thing I’ve ever worked on – and we were just getting started. Judging from the feedback we got when we shared our ideas with friends and colleagues, we might have been onto something; it got people excited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After what was essentially an involved thought experiment, I remain convinced that pro computing is up for grabs. We’re in a moment where comparatively cheap hardware is underutilized by aging, bloated operating systems and software. Microsoft made some slick announcements last week, to be sure, but those are more about improving the ergonomics of some types of digital creative work (mostly visual). There are such bigger opportunities to be had. As thinkers like &lt;a href=&quot;http://worrydream.com/&quot;&gt;Bret Victor&lt;/a&gt; have envisioned, the way computers and the devices that interoperate with them function is so ready for new approaches. What justifies having a general purpose computer running a general purpose operating system in your workspace in an age of connected embedded systems? A pro machine better be doing something special to earn a place on your lap or under your desk in such a world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be no surprise as to why nobody has attempted the sort of ground-up overhauling of pro computing that we mapped out: it’s expensive, slow, and risky to do something big, new, and different. What’s more, we lack the innovative institutions that previously provided cover for the future to take shape: PARC, Bell Labs, et. al. It’s not as if the ideas and talent that will move pro computing forward aren’t out there; it’s a matter of bringing the resources together and having the patience to see something incredibly complex come to fruition. You don’t need me to tell you why that confluence of factors is a rarity in technology today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several months of intense collaboration, life pulled my friend and I in different directions. He’s applying his interest in high-performance computing to the essential problem of curing a vicious disease. The team he works on is making great strides, which in turn underscores the quandry of why pro computing isn’t liable to improve dramatically any time soon: it doesn’t necessarily &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to, because pros can still get shit done with the tools they have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pros don’t quit because their tools are suboptimal. That’s practically the definition of “professional” – a pro gets the damn thing done. A pro user might gripe about the new MacBook Pro, but the next time she needs a new machine, she’s going to buy one anyway because that’s the path of least resistance and she needs to get back to work. That cycle of dependence, along with the need for stability and predictability in one’s tools, makes product incrementalism the norm in pro computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To break that cycle, a company needs to introduce a product that promises such dramatic improvements in productivity and expansion of creative possibility that it’s worth the investment of a pro’s money and time into something unfamiliar. Breakthroughs happen, but rarely, and are usually allowed to come to market only once every last dollar has been wrung out of extant innovations. Don’t have a category-defining new product? You can always graft the smart watch platform you developed onto the keyboard of your flagship laptop. Your customers will be forced to upgrade to it eventually so it’ll look like a win in a few quarters. Good enough!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple will only see an exodus of pro users if it turns out they’ve shipped a machine that truly can’t meet the needs – the actual working limits – of their customers. Armchair grumbles about misfeatures, memory limits, and the wrong ports aren’t the same as being totally unable to do your job because your tools have utterly failed you. I don’t think that’s where most pro users are today, but some are starting to recognize that today’s professional computing tools aren’t likely to carry us forward into new ways of working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I see in the frustrated blog posts from the past few days could be the first rivulets of a sea change … or we could be right back here four years from now. As was clear several years ago, the opportunity for a new approach to pro computing is opening up again. Whether anyone will take it on is another question entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
   <author>
     <name>Alex Payne</name>
     <uri>https://al3x.net/about.html</uri>
   </author>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>So You're Moving To Portland</title>
   <link href="https://al3x.net/2015/11/11/portland.html"/>
   <updated>2015-11-11T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://al3x.net/2015/11/11/portland</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-youre-moving-to-portland&quot;&gt;So You’re Moving To Portland&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://2015.xoxofest.com&quot;&gt;XOXO&lt;/a&gt; festival had its fourth year here in Portland. It took place in a close-in neighborhood on Portland’s east side – the Portland of &lt;em&gt;Portlandia&lt;/em&gt;, the weird and genuine counterpart to the city’s moneyed and buttoned-down west side. XOXO happened around a high school that’s been converted into offices. A local grocery store chain (think a less-precious Whole Foods) is headquartered there. A startup I’m investing in rents space there too. My house is a ten minute walk away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the street is the “vegan mini-mall”, a strip of businesses that omit animal products from what they provide: baked goods, groceries, cookbooks and clothes, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2011/11/no-charred-bones-or-animal-fat-the-search-for-a-vegan-tattoo/246936/&quot;&gt;tattoos&lt;/a&gt;. Naturally, it’s a gathering place for the local vegan community. I’m there a lot, usually at the bakery. (Try the club sandwich and a pumpkin chai bar.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day before XOXO, I asked the woman working the register if she knew about the festival and if they were ready for the additional customers it might bring in. She rolled her eyes. “Yeah, it’s some rich techie bullshit. I think it’s dumb.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conversation we proceeded to have was intense but civil. I offered a limited defense of XOXO: that my friend runs it, that he lives here in Portland and cares about the city; that the event is for independent creative types and not corporate brogrammers. But after that, my standard apologia: I’m in tech but a lot of what tech stands for doesn’t reflect my values, etc. etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it came down to for the cashier is economic displacement. She didn’t really care about XOXO or tech one way or the other. Tech is emblematic, for her and others, of a systemic issue in Portland and beyond: income disparity coupled with limited rental availability means higher rents that are most easily afforded by people arriving from higher-income places and/or working higher-income jobs like those offered in tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cashier didn’t sound angry so much as defeated. “Where are we supposed to go?” she asked. “Back to the midwest? I moved from there. I’m not going back.” I felt defeated too, even as I was describing some of the ways I’ve gotten involved to try to keep Portland affordable and sustainable. Working people don’t have time to spend fighting local political battles and they can’t wait years for solutions to move through legislatures and city councils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cashier and I ended the conversation with the explicit mutual statement that it was good to be able to talk about this stuff, &lt;em&gt;across class lines&lt;/em&gt; going unspoken and implicit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;california-dreaming-of-somewhere-else&quot;&gt;California, Dreaming Of Somewhere Else&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portland is the sort of place you move back to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left after my &lt;a href=&quot;/2012/11/11/alone-together-again.html&quot;&gt;life changed suddenly&lt;/a&gt; several years ago but couldn’t stay away for long. When I was ready to settle down again, Portland was the only place that made sense. It’s the only place I’ve ever lived that feels like home, inclusive of where I grew up (around Washington, DC). That feeling must be shared by all the people I meet who’ve come back here too: those that grew up here, moved away for school, and returned; those that grew up elsewhere, came to Portland for school, and never left; those that took a job, maybe in Silicon Valley or New York, and eventually came home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a transplant, I’m unqualified to speak to feelings of resentment amongst Portland natives beyond the anecdotal. The people I know from here don’t blame newcomers for the city’s changes. The most resentment seems to lie with those who arrived in the early 1990s, when Portland was still rough and the living was cheap. It is no longer the city of &lt;em&gt;My Own Private Idaho&lt;/em&gt;, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hand2mouththeatre.org/time-hustler/&quot;&gt;a local theater company recently explored&lt;/a&gt;. At least, not the Portland that people are moving here for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Californians bear the brunt of the resentment. When I wrote about wanting to leave &lt;a href=&quot;https://al3x.net/2009/10/04/so-youre-moving-to-san-francisco.html&quot;&gt;San Francisco&lt;/a&gt; five years ago, the shine of a new tech gold rush was still on the place. Today, SF is the go-to example of how cities can grow wealthy while still utterly failing their inhabitants; Los Angeles is faring little better. In the Pacific Northwest, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/10/09/technology/seattle-in-midst-of-tech-boom-tries-to-keep-its-soul.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;becoming San Francisco is a nightmare scenario&lt;/a&gt;. In the minds of Portlanders, SF is less a place than a cautionary tale come to life: a shambling horror of greed, NIMBYism, and inept planning. When I meet people who have recently moved to the Bay Area, I half-jokingly tell them that I’ll see them up in Portland in a year or two. Based on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.geekwire.com/2015/a-silicon-valley-exodus-redfin-analysis-finds-that-bay-area-residents-increasingly-looking-for-homes-in-seattle-and-portland/&quot;&gt;real estate data&lt;/a&gt;, that may well be true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not hard to spot affluent people who are scouting out Portland as a possible new home – lifestyle shopping. They’re in the coffee shops loudly taking WebEx meetings between house tours. They’re waiting in long lines for artisanal donuts and ice cream, their children squirming with boredom. They talk about the restaurants – so good, and so &lt;em&gt;affordable!&lt;/em&gt; Everything about Portland is, for them, &lt;em&gt;cute&lt;/em&gt;. Real estate agents are not showing them the neighborhoods where homeless camps have claimed the sidewalks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t begrudge anyone their mobility, nor the impulse to find a better place to raise a family. I also don’t think any amount of resentment will halt the economically inevitable. Portland is the last relatively affordable major city on the West Coast. More people will come, many of them from California, as I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-are-we-supposed-to-go-what-are-we-supposed-to-do&quot;&gt;Where Are We Supposed To Go, What Are We Supposed To Do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gentrification and economic displacement have been perennial topics of conversation for as long as I can remember. These problems go unsolved because, by market logic, they are not problems. Gentrification pushes up property values, ushers in new businesses, and is generally considered to be co-occurrent with “growth”, that all-important yardstick. In the same way that a place can grow rich on fossil fuels while literally poisoning its own wells, a city can gentrify while losing its community, its history, its soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic displacement is a problem that the powerful are content to live with. When the cashier asks “where are we supposed to go?” the market has no answer beyond “someplace you can afford.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portland’s motto is “The City that Works”. Portland plans. That’s a big part of why I live here. My work is systems, and cities are systems, and so I want to live in a city that is a well-run system. Economic displacement is a systemic problem, and so there should be systemic solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the problem of homelessness, the most effective solution seems to be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2015/02/housing-first-solution-to-homelessness-utah&quot;&gt;giving people homes&lt;/a&gt;, which is on the whole cheaper than coping with the many issues caused by a large chronically homeless population via emergency services and shelters. Portland could use some of the recently-declared &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kgw.com/story/news/politics/2015/09/23/mayor-announces-state-emergency-housing-homeless/72685832/&quot;&gt;State of Emergency&lt;/a&gt; funding to address homelessness in this direct way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Articles like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/aponline/2015/11/11/us/ap-us-portland-rental-squeeze.html&quot;&gt;this one from yesterday’s NYT&lt;/a&gt;, on the economic pressures pushing out the artists that helped establish Portland’s cultural capital, take the typical neoliberal line that rent control categorically doesn’t work. Many implementations of rent control are demonstrable failures, while others &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.myeurop.info/2012/06/06/rent-control-a-success-across-northern-europe-5530&quot;&gt;have been successful&lt;/a&gt;; the devil is in the details. In Seattle, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.socialistalternative.org/2015/10/15/kshama-sawant-interview-rent-control/&quot;&gt;City Councilmember Kshama Sawant is making the case for rent control&lt;/a&gt;. Portland is observing that debate and will learn from it. Meanwhile, local renters unions are forming, exploring other avenues to protect tenants rights and combat outsized increases in rent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hopeful that Portland can come up with creative solutions to these problems because I know that there are people here who care. I know property developers who are ready to experiment with radical forms of affordable housing. I know people who want to invest in these sorts of projects. I’ve put money and support behind local entrepreneurs that are creating quality living wage jobs in sectors beyond tech, and who are working with community groups to ensure that underrepresented populations get training and access to those jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re moving to Portland, or thinking about moving to Portland, you have a choice. You can be a consumer of the city – a lifestyle shopper – or you can get involved. You can enjoy the &lt;em&gt;affordable&lt;/em&gt; restaurants and kid-friendly coffee shops and live in comfortable alienation from the problems of the city, or you help ensure that people outside your family also get to enjoy a high quality of life. You can engage in a politics of selfishness and greed – the politics that made San Francisco a cautionary tale – or you can engage in a politics of solidarity and community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portland can continue to be “The City that Works” or it can be yet another city that exploits its workers as it becomes a playground for the wealthy. I know which Portland I want to live in. The cashier at the bakery lives there too.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
   <author>
     <name>Alex Payne</name>
     <uri>https://al3x.net/about.html</uri>
   </author>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Wouldn't Censorship Be Exciting</title>
   <link href="https://al3x.net/2015/06/04/wouldn't-censorship-be-exciting.html"/>
   <updated>2015-06-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://al3x.net/2015/06/04/wouldn't-censorship-be-exciting</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;wouldnt-censorship-be-exciting&quot;&gt;Wouldn’t Censorship Be Exciting&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with a disclaimer: I am not an organizer of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thestrangeloop.com/&quot;&gt;Strange Loop&lt;/a&gt; conference. I’ve presented at it, and for the past several years I’ve co-organized a pre-conference event about emerging programming languages. I’m unable to attend Strange Loop this year, much to my chagrin. Spending a few days in St Louis in September has become an annual routine for me. I care very much about the Strange Loop community, but I do not speak for its organizers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Strange Loop organizers have worked hard to create not just an event in which people fling technical ideas from their mouths into waiting ears, but a community. That community is one of the most diverse and welcoming you’ll find in technology, and that’s no accident. Achieving that diversity has required outreach, intention, and – yes – policing. I know that the language of “safe spaces” is tiresomely overused and sometimes wrongly employed, but it captures the essence of a conference that plays host to speakers and attendees of myriad backgrounds and orientations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday it came to my attention that the organizers of Strange Loop had scheduled a talk by the author of &lt;a href=&quot;http://urbit.org/&quot;&gt;Urbit&lt;/a&gt;. Urbit’s author, like many of us, writes online. In particular, he writes about a form of far-right politics that could be described as fascistic. Uncomfortable, to be sure, but as someone who publicly holds political views that stray from the mainstream, who am I to judge?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I joined the call for Urbit’s author’s invitation to be rescinded is not his political views. Had he spoken, it wouldn’t be the first time I’ve interacted with someone who espouses a politics divergent from my own at a technology conference, and nor would I hope it would be the last. I value a diversity of viewpoints, as must anyone committed to democratic processes. The fact that the person in question explores far-right viewpoints in his writing in no way led me to call for his rejection. I am unafraid of bad ideas; they are but litter on the street, blowing about the ankles, destined for the darkness of the storm drain by their own pathetic motion. Let them roll. Let them drown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strewn throughout the Urbit author’s writings are statements in support of racism and slavery. To my mind, this is where the line is crossed from the abstract debate of politics into something more visceral and emotional: hate. Hate is a necessary component of any defense of racism, slavery, and other dehumanizing practices. Hate is necessary to reduce a person to a commodity or strip them of rights based on innate traits. Couch it all you want in the trappings of academic writing: hate is always laid bare for what it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hate has no place in the Strange Loop community, nor in any community with a future. Some have found it convenient and exciting to assume that Urbit’s author was uninvited – nay, censored! – due to his political views. Trust me: those views could not be less frightening or less interesting. What does concern me is the idea that Strange Loop attendees would no longer feel welcome because an avowed racist and proponent of slavery has been given a tacit endorsement by virtue of his speaking slot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That speaking slot, of course, was not intended for a discussion of politics or race or slavery. It was intended for a discussion of software. And wouldn’t it be tidy to assume that we can separate the two, leaving our identities backstage as we step up to a podium of pure ideas? Untidily, this is not how the real world functions. The views we commit to in public travel with us, for better and for worse. What we believe helps us form community, and so too can it repel others away from us. In our communities, we establish norms and standards. Violating those standards often results in expulsion. The views we commit to have social consequences – yes, even at a technology conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because these hateful views laze within self-styled political writing, some have claimed political discrimination. That would indeed be a scandal, but it’s not what happened here. The community in which Urbit’s author travels feeds on outraged reactions to their views. They are, after all, fascistic: uninterested in consensus and validated by fear. All the more reason to invent a scandal where none exists, offering a moment of relevancy and meaning in what must be a tiresome day of hauling around stale, warmed-over ideas under the forgettable banner of the “neoreactionary”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author of Urbit has not been censored. His software is readily available for examination and discussion online. I should know, having examined and discussed it without Birkenstocked progressive thugs dragging me from desk. There are meetups about Urbit in a number of cities. Other conferences may choose to host him. You could even run your own conference and invite him. Ah, but then where would you find the time to be so deliciously outraged? You’d be busy handling the logistics, the promotion, the speaker selection, and indeed the community policing that goes into running a successful conference. You might even have attendees of your own with concerns to accommodate. How is one supposed to play the victim, crying “thoughtcrime!”, with so much to do?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
   <author>
     <name>Alex Payne</name>
     <uri>https://al3x.net/about.html</uri>
   </author>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Investing in The Working World</title>
   <link href="https://al3x.net/2015/06/02/investing-in-the-working-world.html"/>
   <updated>2015-06-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://al3x.net/2015/06/02/investing-in-the-working-world</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;investing-in-the-working-world&quot;&gt;Investing in The Working World&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Business with a conscience” is no longer a fringe mentality. Witness &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mckinsey.com/insights/strategy/business_and_society_in_the_coming_decades&quot;&gt;top Walmart executives writing for consulting giant McKinsey&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Increasingly, a basic expectation among customers, governments, and communities will be that the companies they do business with provide a significant net positive return for society at large, not just for investors. This will be a part of the implicit contract or license to operate.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This changing reality raises questions not just for corporate executives, but for the investors who back them, from angels to hedge funds to household shareholders. How do we make a return on our investment – thus enabling future investments – without extracting more value than we create in the process?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere between philanthropy and profiteering lie the murky waters of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impact_investing&quot;&gt;impact investing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socially_responsible_investing&quot;&gt;socially responsible investing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triple_bottom_line&quot;&gt;triple bottom line&lt;/a&gt;, and their ilk. For investors who want more out of their dollar than pure return, there are  no shortage of socially-minded strategies, accounting frameworks, and certifications. The challenge is navigating around the buzzwords and greenwashing to ventures with a genuine likelihood of sustainable positive outcomes for investors and communities alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my capacity as an angel investor I’ve tried to fund young companies that offer products and services with a clear social benefit, from health to disaster relief to global connectivity. Yet, venture-backed startups are operating under an extreme form of traditional capital investment that often sees businesses abandon their values and customer commitments along the road to riches – if they even make it. As a kind of socially-minded hedge against the startup pressure-cooker, I looked far and wide for investment opportunities that address structural issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://theworkingworld.org/&quot;&gt;The Working World&lt;/a&gt; (TWW) is, I believe, such an opportunity. They describe themselves as “venture capitalists with a radical social mission: to lend people the tools to democratically build lasting wealth for themselves, their businesses, and their communities”. By investing in worker-owned enterprises, TWW offers the all-too-rare chance for harmonious collaboration between labor and capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooperatives offer a proven long-term model for enriching and empowering working communities. TWW acts as a non-profit facilitator, matching money from investors like me to cooperative businesses around the world. They stay directly involved in the companies they fund, building mutually respectful relationships that weather the ups and downs of the global market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, TWW founder Brendan Martin incorporated my feedback into a new investment vehicle. From the investor’s side, it’s not unlike putting money into a hedge fund. For TWW’s part, they have leeway to accomodate the businesses they work with, offering fair terms and flexible repayment timelines. Returns will help to cover TWW’s modest operating expenses and can be readily reinvested in other cooperative businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new fund expands on the decade of success that TWW has seen, first in Argentina and Nicaragua, and now right here in the US. They give workers the same benefit of shared risk tolerance that high-flying startups get from VC firms; only successful investments are repaid. Unlike so many of those richly-capitalized startups that go up in smoke, TWW’s democratic worker cooperatives have thrived, delivering a nearly perfect repayment rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cooperative model lets working people control their own destinies. The experience of cooperative enterprises like Spain’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mondragon-corporation.com/eng/&quot;&gt;Mondragon Corporation&lt;/a&gt; make clear that this bottom-up approach yields jobs, revenues, and technological advancement over the long term. Indeed, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/cameronkeng/2014/12/18/if-apple-was-a-worker-cooperative-each-employee-would-earn-at-least-403k/&quot;&gt;a Forbes contributor argued&lt;/a&gt;, even white-collar workers at large companies might be better off in cooperatives: the lowest-paid employee at Apple would have taken home $403,000 last year if the tech giant converted to worker-ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to my continuing collaboration with Brendan and the rest of the team at TWW as they expand opportunities for working people around the globe. I encourage other investors to &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.ncrp.org/2015/05/investing-in-worker-cooperatives.html&quot;&gt;investigate the untapped potential of cooperatives&lt;/a&gt;, and to join the $1M I’ve put into The Working World’s new fund.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
   <author>
     <name>Alex Payne</name>
     <uri>https://al3x.net/about.html</uri>
   </author>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Jacobin</title>
   <link href="https://al3x.net/2015/03/03/jacobin.html"/>
   <updated>2015-03-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://al3x.net/2015/03/03/jacobin</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;jacobin&quot;&gt;Jacobin&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several years as an enthusiastic reader and supporter, it’s my pleasure to announce that I’m joining the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jacobinmag.com/&quot;&gt;Jacobin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; advisory board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; describes itself as “a leading voice of the American left, offering socialist perspectives on politics, economics, and culture.” The Jacobin Foundation publishes a quarterly magazine in print and digital formats along with regular online content. In recent months, &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; has expanded a network of international reading groups and promoted efforts like &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/jacobin/class-action-presented-by-the-ctus-core-and-jacobi&quot;&gt;Class Action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, a booklet for rank-and-file teacher groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chances are good that &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; has already crossed your path. Their articles and essays show up across social media and popular online communities like Reddit. Jacobin is regularly referenced in widely-circulated publications like &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Rolling Stone&lt;/em&gt;. The magazine’s reach and readership are growing rapidly, impacting the wider media landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognizing that it’s not every day that an angel investor and erstwhile entrepreneur backs a socialist publication, I’d like to preemptively answer some questions that may arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preemptively-answered-questions&quot;&gt;Preemptively Answered Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is this like when that Facebook guy bought that political magazine?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, this isn’t like when &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2012/03/12/148247430/facebook-co-founder-chris-hughes-is-buying-the-new-republic&quot;&gt;Chris Hughes bought &lt;em&gt;The New Republic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in early 2012. For one thing, the Jacobin Foundation is a non-profit organization. I’m making a substantial donation, but there’s nothing to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, unlike Hughes, I’m not taking any kind of operational role at &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt;. I greatly admire what publisher &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sunraysunray&quot;&gt;Bhaskar Sunkara&lt;/a&gt; and creative director &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/remeike&quot;&gt;Remeike Forbes&lt;/a&gt; have built alongside the rest of Jacobin’s staff and contributors. Indeed, &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; is run more efficiently than many for-profit startups I’ve come across – they would have been fine without my help. My goal in donating is to support their continued growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the interest of full disclosure: &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jacobinmag.com/2014/06/atlas-smug/&quot;&gt;republished an essay of mine&lt;/a&gt; on their blog before my donation was finalized. I receive no compensation from &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; for my writing. While I do not foresee becoming a regular contributor, I may write for them in the future; that’s entirely at the editors’ discretion. I’m supporting &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; to amplify the many important voices on the American and international left, not my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; is both a destination for readers interested in broadening their political horizons and an intellectual space in which committed leftists can debate. I don’t agree with everything &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; prints, but that’s not the point. I value the project holistically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So you’re some kind of communist then?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it has &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marxism&quot;&gt;Marxist&lt;/a&gt; roots, Jacobin is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic_socialism&quot;&gt;democratic socialist&lt;/a&gt; publication. The United States has a long history of radical movements who fought for a democratic and just society. &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; follows in their footsteps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dsausa.org/&quot;&gt;Democratic Socialists of America&lt;/a&gt; (to whom I also donate but have no formal relationship with) have an easily-digested &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dsausa.org/what_is_democratic_socialism&quot;&gt;FAQ&lt;/a&gt; that addresses many of the questions Americans are likely to have about the tradition and its intersection with our political history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Democratic socialist politics are my politics. I’m a socialist because I want to live in a just society. More than that, I want to live in a &lt;em&gt;survivable&lt;/em&gt; society. The form of capitalism we live under does not present a viable future ecologically, economically, or socially. It is a system designed for the creation and preservation of capital, not human life. I’m a socialist because I believe that the wealth of society can best be harnessed through cooperation, not competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I thought all you tech people are libertarians?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vocal minority of tech workers identify as libertarians. But it’s been my experience that most people who work in technology are no more or less politicized than other Americans. I’m hopeful that this is changing as our industry fully embraces the political responsibility that comes with the incredible economic and social power we wield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s encouraging to see visible tech personalities like Y Combinator’s Sam Altman catch up to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Who-Owns-Future-Jaron-Lanier-ebook/dp/B008J2AEY8/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1425403819&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;Jaron Lanier&lt;/a&gt; and others who have been addressing the issue of tech’s impact on labor for years now. Altman &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.samaltman.com/the-software-revolution&quot;&gt;recently wrote&lt;/a&gt; that “drastic wealth inequality is likely to be one of the biggest social problems of the next 20 years,” following up with the obversation that “the social safety net will have to trend up with the development of technology.” To inspire real solutions to these problems, why not look to the intellectual community that’s been thinking about how to resolve economic inequality and build effective social safety nets for well over a century?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technological development could hurt or help ordinary workers – much depends on the political context under which innovations emerge. &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; generally takes a critical but optimistic view about the relationship between technology and labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why waste your time with this stuff?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, socialist candidates and parties have been elected to governments around the world. Today, Americans have voted in self-described socialist politicians to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernie_Sanders&quot;&gt;US Senate&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kshama_Sawant&quot;&gt;Seattle City Council&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change doesn’t happen overnight, particularly in a system dominated by private interests. But the intellectual foundation for social progress in this country was laid over centuries of political and philosophical struggle. I’m backing Jacobin to help ensure that the evolution of American politics continues – or, indeed, accelerates. In the meantime, by supporting the struggles of public sector workers and others fighting for immediate reforms, &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; is already making an impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Isn’t supporting socialism counterproductive for a well-off person?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under a social democratic system that provides its citizens with the universal health care, basic income, and other protections that every human being deserves, I would likely be paying more in taxes. I view higher taxes as a vanishingly small price for a healthier and more just society. True privilege is the ability to rectify inequity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A truly wealthy society would not tolerate the exploitation and precarity that has become the American norm. The slim economic recovery that is currently taking place is not benefitting workers and the vanishing middle class. It is no longer radical to suggest that higher taxes for the wealthy are neccesary to address this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need only look to history to see what happens to the rich in such circumstances. I echo the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.politico.com/magazine/story/2014/06/the-pitchforks-are-coming-for-us-plutocrats-108014.html&quot;&gt;sentiments of early Amazon investor Nick Hanauer&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“[T]here is no example in human history where wealth accumulated like this and the pitchforks didn’t eventually come out. You show me a highly unequal society, and I will show you a police state. Or an uprising. There are no counterexamples. None. It’s not if, it’s when.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Hanauer, I don’t believe that “smart capitalism” will keep the pitchforks at bay. What we’re witnessing today is not capitalism failing but capitalism at its most successful. As long as we persist in the delusion that there exists a form of capitalism that isn’t inherently exploitative and self-destructive, we will find ourselves – rich and poor alike – eternally on the precipice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don’t you owe capitalism for the financial privilege that enables you to support this cause?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A public school teacher fostered my love of computers. The information technologies that I built my career on were seeded with government dollars. State pension funds are major stakeholders in the venture capital funds that have invested in the businesses I’ve been involved in. I could even argue that I owe my success to the quality educations that my parents received in an era when the coffers of the state-run University of California were full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Privatization has no grand claim to the success of the American entrepreneur. In kind, the entrepreneur should have no grand claim to massive private wealth. The modern world is hugely interdependent, yet individuals still hoard or deploy great treasure as they see fit; we have not left feudalism behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we shouldn’t outright dismiss the impulses behind all philanthropy, relying on the charitable whims and wishes of a scant few is an incomplete strategy for furthering a stable and prosperous society. Bill Gates &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gatesnotes.com/Books/Why-Inequality-Matters-Capital-in-21st-Century-Review&quot;&gt;has come around&lt;/a&gt; to the fact that, in his words, “[c]apitalism does not self-correct toward greater equality”. Yet the convicted monopolist is evidently unready to recognize that no individual should control billions. Though I give to a variety of causes and non-profit organizations, I don’t believe that philanthropy is a fair bargain for the damage done by capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The circumstances that allow me to support &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; are the byproduct of a broken system. My obligation, then, is not to capitalism but to a more just socialist alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;closing-thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalism is an extremist ideology. We have forgotten this in America, where the economic system that’s stifled our democracy and bankrupted our communities is presented to us from birth as right, inevitable, enduring, and unquestionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many, a just and well-functioned government is hard to imagine after years of political gridlock and corruption. I recognize that it’s asking a lot to imagine that things could be different, much less better. We’ve been conditioned to accept that the state is inherently incompetent, that free markets are inherently optimal, and that private wealth and consumption are the only drivers of growth. These pernicious fallacies are self-fulfilling prophecies. We must end them by ending our belief in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unwavering capitalists would like to dismiss &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; and the possibilities of a renewed American democratic socialist movement as a mere overreaction to the Great Recession. This ignores our country’s long history of labor movements, but no matter. We were here yesterday and we’ll be here tomorrow. &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; has taken up the banner today, and I think they’re doing a damn fine job of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magazine’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jacobinmag.com/issue/paint-the-town-red/&quot;&gt;most recent issue&lt;/a&gt; examines the past, present, and future of cities through a socialist lens. It’s a superb jumping-off point for new readers. Even more relevant to my audience, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jacobinmag.com/issue-17/&quot;&gt;upcoming Spring 2015 issue&lt;/a&gt; focuses on technology. If you’re just discovering &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; now, you picked a great time to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m proud to support &lt;em&gt;Jacobin&lt;/em&gt; in their continuing exploration of American democratic socialism. I hope you’ll join me by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jacobinmag.com/subscribe/&quot;&gt;subscribing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jacobinmag.com/donate/&quot;&gt;donating&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jacobinmag.com/reading-groups/&quot;&gt;joining a reading group&lt;/a&gt;, or just spreading the word.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
   <author>
     <name>Alex Payne</name>
     <uri>https://al3x.net/about.html</uri>
   </author>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Meditation and Performance</title>
   <link href="https://al3x.net/2015/02/24/meditation-and-performance.html"/>
   <updated>2015-02-24T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://al3x.net/2015/02/24/meditation-and-performance</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;meditation-and-performance&quot;&gt;Meditation and Performance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our notion of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knowledge_worker&quot;&gt;knowledge work&lt;/a&gt; is approaching its sixth decade. Having exhausted management fads and novel office furniture arrangements, attention has now turned to meditation as the next performance enhancer for cerebral endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness meditation, a popular Buddhist-derived contemplative practice, has become a business buzzword over the past several years. You’ll find mindfulness heralded in &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2015/01/mindfulness-can-literally-change-your-brain&quot;&gt;The Harvard Business Review&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fastcompany.com/3038639/5-ways-to-embrace-mindfulness-at-work&quot;&gt;Fast Company&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://articles.latimes.com/2013/feb/23/business/la-fi-meditation-management-20130224&quot;&gt;The LA Times&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/kathycaprino/2014/02/12/5-mindfulness-steps-that-guarantee-increased-success-and-vitality/&quot;&gt;Forbes&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/search?N=0+4294967064&amp;amp;Ntt=mindfulness&quot;&gt;The HBR again and again and again&lt;/a&gt;. Google has a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/sustainable-business/google-meditation-mindfulness-technology&quot;&gt;famous mindfulness program&lt;/a&gt;. NYU is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/caitlin-weaver-/nyus-new-mindfulness-in-business-initiative_b_5786958.html&quot;&gt;teaching mindfulness at their business school&lt;/a&gt;. Mindfulness will &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.recruiter.co.uk/personal-dev/2015/02/three-tips-to-be-a-more-mindful-and-successful-recruiter/&quot;&gt;make you a better recruiter&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;http://abcnews.go.com/Health/secret-weapon-ceos-basketball-pros-zone/story?id=29051073&quot;&gt;better CEO, and a better pro basketball player&lt;/a&gt;. There is an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/soren-gordhamer/welcome-to-wisdom-20_b_4789960.html&quot;&gt;exclusive conference&lt;/a&gt; at which executives can explore the intersection of mindfulness and business. Here in Portland, a former Simple coworker has cofounded a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.portlandmonthlymag.com/news-and-profiles/culture/articles/mindfulness-hush-meditation-february-2015&quot;&gt;meditation center aimed at professionals&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, from America’s heartland, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indianagazette.com/news/home-lifestyle/meditation-is-settling-into-the-mainstream,21543928/&quot;&gt;Indiana Gazette&lt;/a&gt; says “meditation is settling into the mainstream”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was 13, I had an intimate conversation with a family friend. Having earned my trust with her utter genuineness, I shared with her the whirl of conflicting, self-undermining thoughts that gathered in my head day after day – in retrospect, early signs of depression. Being the rare adult with the kindness not to condescend to the young, she listened and commiserated. “I get that too,” she said. “Meditating helps. It helps a lot.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It did help, and still does when I make time for it. I’m by no means an expert on mindfulness in particular or meditation in general, but I can say that I’ve had an on-again, off-again meditation practice for more than 15 years. I’ve read a lot on the subject, from research to scripture. I’ve taken classes, but never gone on a retreat. My personal practice is secular, yet my appreciation for meditation’s unarguable religious roots is sincere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I read about the general spread of mindfulness, I’m gladdened and encouraged. It is a simple thing, available as freely as breath to practically every human, that can steady our faltering steps on the path of life. I would not begrudge anyone their mindfulness practice, no matter what form it takes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I read about mindfulness in the business world, though, I’m left with uneasy questions. Apparently, I’m not the only one. In their review of David Gelles’ &lt;em&gt;Mindful Work&lt;/em&gt;, the Financial Times &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/54dc5d8c-a09a-11e4-8ad8-00144feab7de.html&quot;&gt;hits the nail on the head&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Is mindfulness really a neutral instrument that can be used for any end — or is it inextricably bound up with the elimination of selfishness, the cultivation of compassion and the rejection of materialism? And might not promoting mindfulness among one’s employees be a bit risky as a result — because if one succeeds, they might stop bothering with anything so trivial as profits?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing in the wake of a protest action against the Wisdom 2.0 conference, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/ron-purser/google-misses-a-lesson_b_4900285.html&quot;&gt;a pair of professors cut deeper&lt;/a&gt;, accusing the event’s corporate hosts of selling a hollow “McMindfulness”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Many in the mindfulness — and Buddhist — community have been seduced by what Google and the Wisdom 2.0 crowd is doing. After all, it’s mindfulness, and maybe it will make corporations kinder, gentler capitalist entities. But mindfulness has escaped its moral moorings. Without a principled anchor, mindfulness is a renegade technology on the loose, and the conspicuous absence of an explicit ethical framework in corporate mindfulness programs reflects and mirrors the already fraught relationship these businesses have with regards to social and environmental responsibility. […] What they insist on calling ‘wisdom’ does not extend beyond corporate cultural values.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on the more explicitly Buddhist aspects of mindfulness, &lt;em&gt;Salon&lt;/em&gt; recently &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.salon.com/2014/03/05/gentrifying_the_dharma_how_the_1_is_hijacking_mindfulness/&quot;&gt;addressed the turmoil&lt;/a&gt; within this movement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Most American converts still see Buddhism as a path to individual spiritual development through meditation. Few convert groups focus on building fellowship and camaraderie, engaging families or getting involved in their local community. Even fewer regularly do service work, much less activism. In that environment, groups like the Buddhist Peace Fellowship and Buddhist Global Relief often struggle for support.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most damning, Vietnamese monk Thich Nhat Hanh – likely the single person on the planet most responsible for the spread of mindfulness – had &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/sustainable-business/thich-nhat-hanh-mindfulness-google-tech&quot;&gt;this to say&lt;/a&gt; about his tradition’s new business suit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If you consider mindfulness as a means of having a lot of money, then you have not touched its true purpose. It may look like the practice of mindfulness but inside there’s no peace, no joy, no happiness produced. It’s just an imitation. If you don’t feel the energy of brotherhood, of sisterhood, radiating from your work, that is not mindfulness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current adoption of mindfulness in business is wrapped up in the idea of the “quantified self”, an individualistic outcropping of the corporate habit of foisting difficult decisions onto (often questionable) statistical models. Research has made discussing meditation socially acceptable amongst the self-serious. With data in hand, mindfulness is no longer woo-woo: there is a chart, and the line on the chart goes up and to the right, and so the monk is given a badge and pointed towards the office cafeteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not, as I said, begrudge anyone their mindfulness practice. If you are meditating because adding ten additional IQ points appeals to you, or you want to shave a few minutes off your daily programming tasks, there is no harm in those goals. I’ve enjoyed such benefits from my own practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness is so much more than a performance enhancing tool, though. If that’s what you’re searching for, you’re better off with caffeine; there’s better data on it, anyway. A mindfulness practice can bring clarity and focus, but it should also raise questions. Questions like: “why do I want to be better at my job?”, “who benefits if I’m more productive?”, and “does my labor reduce suffering more than sitting in mindful contemplation?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve progressed in my career, my mindfulness practice has progressed as well. No coincidence, then, that I find myself more radical and questioning of our capitalist system at an age (and in a tax bracket) that’s most commonly associated with creeping conservatism. I credit my practice not just for helping me to survive the stresses of work, but for putting that work in context. Sometimes, that new context has led me to serious reevaluations of my priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first things a new meditator learns is that sitting in contemplation is not always pleasant. Your body may ache, and you are forced to feel it. Your heart may ache, and there is nothing to distract you from it. We sit with our suffering, and in doing so we foster the empathy that lets us genuinely engage with the suffering of others. If you have not yet had that experience in your own practice, you are fortunate, because it is there, waiting to transform you, when you’re ready.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
   <author>
     <name>Alex Payne</name>
     <uri>https://al3x.net/about.html</uri>
   </author>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What I've Been Doing</title>
   <link href="https://al3x.net/2015/01/30/what-ive-been-doing.html"/>
   <updated>2015-01-30T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://al3x.net/2015/01/30/what-ive-been-doing</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-ive-been-doing&quot;&gt;What I’ve Been Doing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“So, uh, what exactly do you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; these days?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hear this question and I smile awkwardly, because I’m still not sure how to answer it concisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Distant friends and professional acquaintances have admitted, upon reconnecting, that they’ve sort of lost track of me since I &lt;a href=&quot;/2012/07/25/moving-on.html&quot;&gt;left Simple&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t blame them: I’ve been all over the place, geographically and work-wise. It doesn’t help that my periodic hiatuses from Twitter have turned semi-permanent, drying up that steady drip of personal context out to whoever wants it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an enjoyable full-time stint at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dobt.co/&quot;&gt;DOBT&lt;/a&gt; for the first half of 2014. At that point the company decided to sharpen their focus down to a single product, and not one I had much to contribute to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior and since, I’ve been doing a lot. About as much as I ever have, really, just not neatly packaged up with a job title and a company name and a business card. This is what’s been keeping me busy over the past couple years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;consulting&quot;&gt;Consulting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve consulted on API design, building developer communities, systems architecture, devops, and language design, amongst other things. My clients have included &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paywithcover.com/&quot;&gt;Cover&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://brickalloy.com/&quot;&gt;Brick Alloy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://orchestrate.io/&quot;&gt;Orchestrate&lt;/a&gt;, and a couple of stealth companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently spent a week on-site at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.consumerfinance.gov/&quot;&gt;Consumer Financial Protection Bureau&lt;/a&gt; in DC. They have a great team and an incredibly important mission. Getting to know them was a blast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My next consulting project is overhauling a web-based piece for a notable contemporary artist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prototyping&quot;&gt;Prototyping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several friends have come to me with product ideas in need of a proof-of-concept implementation. Working with friends can be tricky, especially when everyone’s juggling other commitments, but I’ve had fun building these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teaching&quot;&gt;Teaching&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did two rotations as a resident at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hackerschool.com/&quot;&gt;Hacker School&lt;/a&gt; in NYC. I’ll be in Denver at &lt;a href=&quot;http://turing.io/&quot;&gt;Turing&lt;/a&gt; the first week in March. In a sea of questionable “code schools”, those two are doing it right, to my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;investing-and-advising&quot;&gt;Investing and Advising&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve continued to make angel investments in select technology startups. My thesis, such as it is, is a combination of “invest in what you know” and investing for social impact. That’s led to a modest portfolio with concentrations in API-driven products, devops tools, products that facilitate team communication, and health data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also made larger-dollar investments outside of tech. Those deals have required learning about unfamiliar and rapidly-evolving industries and markets. I find that kind of research really fun, but it can be a job in and of itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;giving&quot;&gt;Giving&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without question, the thing I’ve been enjoying the most is giving people time and money; it’s just the best. Giving smartly, though, can be as time-intensive as researching for-profit investments. Plus, as more non-profits leverage technology, there’s at least as much advisory work to be done in that world as there is for startups. I love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;over-the-bridge&quot;&gt;Over The Bridge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what I’ve been up to, all while moving, traveling a whole bunch, writing, speaking, &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/09/16/thoughts-on-five-years-of-emerging-languages.html&quot;&gt;organizing a conference&lt;/a&gt;, and dealing with family health matters. That doesn’t answer it all, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Are you going to do another startup?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get this one a lot, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;/2013/05/23/letter-to-a-young-programmer.html&quot;&gt;written before&lt;/a&gt;, I don’t believe in startups for the sake of startups. If there’s something I’m really passionate about, and I have the right people with me, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the problem we want to solve is best attacked in the form of a startup, I’d consider it. But I’m not going to jump back into another startup just because that’s what people with my experience are supposed to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like early-stage projects a lot. I’ve found many ways to support them – for-profit and non-profit alike – in full-time roles and otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Workin’ on something big?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I know: I’m happier and healthier than I’ve ever been. I attribute at least some of that to the freedom and flexibility I’ve had over the past couple years. Without creating that stable foundation, I wasn’t ever going to accomplish anything again. Good health, mental and physical, is invaluable. I was &lt;a href=&quot;/2010/09/07/startup-health.html&quot;&gt;striving for it&lt;/a&gt; years ago, but actually getting there took more: more time, more energy, more experience, and more patience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could see myself continuing to enjoy the mishmash of things that have kept me busy. Not being able to tersely explain what I do is really the only downside. Still, I feel like I have another big project in me. Having made a couple of false starts, I’m getting comfortable with taking my time to find that next thing, or to let it find me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other morning, a heavy fog spilled over the hills, enshrouding the city totally. As I drove over a bridge, past and future all but disappeared. I could see two car lengths ahead, two car lengths behind. The top of the bridge and the river below were gone, consumed in water vapor. I turned the radio off and enjoyed the car’s low humming reassurance of forward motion. There was nothing else, and it was enough.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
   <author>
     <name>Alex Payne</name>
     <uri>https://al3x.net/about.html</uri>
   </author>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Thoughts On Five Years of Emerging Languages</title>
   <link href="https://al3x.net/2014/09/16/thoughts-on-five-years-of-emerging-languages.html"/>
   <updated>2014-09-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://al3x.net/2014/09/16/thoughts-on-five-years-of-emerging-languages</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;thoughts-on-five-years-of-emerging-languages&quot;&gt;Thoughts On Five Years of Emerging Languages&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Wednesday will mark five years of &lt;a href=&quot;http://emerginglangs.com/&quot;&gt;Emerging Languages&lt;/a&gt;, the showcase for new programming languages that I &lt;a href=&quot;https://al3x.net/2009/06/15/emerging-languages-conference.html&quot;&gt;dreamed up&lt;/a&gt; back in 2009. As we approach half a decade and well over fifty total presentations, I’ve been reflecting on where the event has been and how the language landscape has changed since we began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first year, &lt;a href=&quot;http://emerginglangs.com/archive/2010.html&quot;&gt;2010&lt;/a&gt;, was a big one. Several of the languages presented that year have since broken out into the mainstream, particularly &lt;a href=&quot;http://clojure.org/&quot;&gt;Clojure&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://golang.org/&quot;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://coffeescript.org/&quot;&gt;CoffeeScript&lt;/a&gt;. The inaugural presentation culminated in a wonderfully tense moment, one that perfectly captures the push and pull of academic and industrial forces in the world of programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Go co-creator Rob Pike wrapped up his talk and opened up the floor for Q&amp;amp;A, an audience member didn’t hesitate to address the elephant in the server room:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Rob, why have you shipped a language in 2010 that seemingly ignores the last 30+ years of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Programming_language_theory&quot;&gt;PLT&lt;/a&gt; research?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could attempt to reconstruct Pike’s arch-yet-erudite response, but Go’s significant adoption since is an even better rebuttal. Go’s design does seem far more informed by industrial practice than academic research. Go asserts that a productive systems language is a conservative one. There are few concepts in Go that date more recently than the mid-1970s, and the language has continued to maintain a trim surface area in subsequent releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m beginning to write my second real-world Go project as I head to St Louis for this year’s Emerging Languages. When working in Go I feel, I must admit, like a traitor to the cause of advancing programming languages. What I miss in terms of higher-level abstractions and functional features is largely made up for by Go’s superb tooling, documentation, and core libraries. But oh, the guilt!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tooling-and-editing&quot;&gt;Tooling and Editing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, Emerging Languages has joined up with &lt;a href=&quot;http://alarmingdevelopment.org/&quot;&gt;Jonathan Edwards&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dreamsongs.com/Bio.html&quot;&gt;Richard Gabriel&lt;/a&gt;. I reached out after they announced their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.future-programming.org/&quot;&gt;Future Programming Workshop&lt;/a&gt;, as I thought our events had significant overlap. They kindly agreed. Our combined event will broaden the focus of Emerging Languages to include the tooling &lt;em&gt;around&lt;/em&gt; languages, something we’ve only touched on in previous years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One could read the success of Go as an indictment of contemporary PLT, but I prefer to see it as a reminder of just how much language tooling matters. Perhaps even more critical, Go’s lean syntax, selective semantics, and cautiously-chosen feature set demonstrate the importance of a strong editorial voice in a language’s design and evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having co-authored a book on &lt;a href=&quot;http://scala-lang.org/&quot;&gt;Scala&lt;/a&gt;, it’s been painful to see systems programmers in my community express frustration with the ambitious hybrid language. I’ve watched them abandon ship and swim back to the familiar shores of Java, or alternately into the uncharted waters of Clojure, Go, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rust-lang.org/&quot;&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt;. A pity, but not entirely surprising if we’re being honest with ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Go, Scala has struggled with tooling from its inception. More than that, Scala has had a growing editorial problem. Every shop I know that’s been successful with Scala has limited itself to some subset of the language. Meanwhile, in pursuit of enterprise developers, its surface area has expanded in seemingly every direction. The folks behind Scala have, thankfully, taken notice: &lt;a href=&quot;http://scala-lang.org/news/roadmap-next&quot;&gt;upcoming releases&lt;/a&gt; are promised to focus on simplicity, clarity, and better tooling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;virtual-machines-and-flying-solo&quot;&gt;Virtual Machines and Flying Solo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CoffeeScript and Clojure were, as mentioned above, two other breakout languages from our 2010 event. There are further lessons for language authors to be learned from their examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CoffeeScript has proven robust enough to, amongst other things, &lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/&quot;&gt;power a desktop text editor&lt;/a&gt;. Its success has unquestionably put pressure on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ECMAScript&quot;&gt;ECMAScript&lt;/a&gt; committee to deliver much-belated improvements to the self-styled “language of the web”. Yet, there is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/trends/explore#q=coffeescript&quot;&gt;visible crest and tapering-off&lt;/a&gt; of interest in CoffeeScript. A &lt;a href=&quot;http://oscargodson.com/posts/why-i-dont-use-coffeescript.html&quot;&gt;common takeaway&lt;/a&gt; is that CoffeeScript improved on too little over plain JavaScript while &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.walkercoderanger.com/blog/2014/03/coffeescript-isnt-the-answer/&quot;&gt;complicating the toolchain&lt;/a&gt; too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2008 I &lt;a href=&quot;https://al3x.net/2007/12/20/big-in-2008-dynamic-languages-atop-high.html&quot;&gt;had a hunch&lt;/a&gt; that VMs designed for high-level languages (ex: Java and the JVM, Erlang and its VM, JavaScript and its many VMs) were going to flourish as host platforms for even higher-level languages. That prediction has largely come true, but as an implementation strategy it’s starting to outstay its welcome. CoffeeScript being set aside for JavaScript and &lt;a href=&quot;http://codahale.com/the-rest-of-the-story/&quot;&gt;Scala being set aside for Java&lt;/a&gt; are not, I think, isolated cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Clojure community has made periodic noises of longing regarding a port to &lt;a href=&quot;http://llvm.org/&quot;&gt;LLVM&lt;/a&gt;, which would liberate it from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://martintrojer.github.io/clojure/2014/04/05/the-clojure-repl-a-blessing-and-a-curse/&quot;&gt;frustrations of the JVM&lt;/a&gt;, albeit with significant effort. (One &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/halgari/mjolnir&quot;&gt;Clojure-on-LLVM project&lt;/a&gt; has 175 stars on GitHub; a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/artagnon/rhine&quot;&gt;Clojure-inspired Lisp on LLVM&lt;/a&gt; boasts nearly 400.) While Clojure offers a bounty of the sort of novel language features that Go has passed up, having to understand the JVM in order to confidently use the language has proven a consistent stumbling block for new Clojurists. The same &lt;a href=&quot;http://telladifferentstory.tumblr.com/post/68164735574/tough-day-in-clojurescript-land&quot;&gt;friction&lt;/a&gt; can be heard in discussions of ClojureScript. Like CoffeeScript, it’s a marked improvement over JavaScript, but for many developers that may not be enough to warrant the cognitive overhead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the devil’s bargain made by such stranger-on-a-strange-VM languages: there is nothing you truly get for free from the host platform. Someone pays the price, whether up front by weary compiler authors or passed on to language users as unwelcome technical debt. At some point the productivity gains yielded by higher-than-high-level languages give way to VM parameter tuning, messy interoperability work, and even competition with the host language as it appropriates the best features of its guests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The era of shipping new languages on existing VMs brought language authors a lot of flexibility and experimentation. With a solid, established foundation to build on, individuals and small teams could ship practical languages in a short period of time. The benefits of this strategy are not to be dismissed, but nor are the downsides that we’ve since discovered in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I’m being held to another prediction, it’s that the insurgent languages five years from now will be – like Go, Rust, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://julialang.org/&quot;&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt; – untethered by a host VM. The low-power, high-connectivity Internet of Things world we’re moving towards leaves far less room for fat VMs. The languages that haven’t abandoned their hosts by then will be thought of as baggage from the resource-inefficient early days of cloud computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-ask-why&quot;&gt;Why Ask Why?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the last day of the first Emerging Languages I was interviewed about the event by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.technologyreview.com/news/419956/new-languages-and-why-we-need-them/&quot;&gt;MIT Technology Review&lt;/a&gt;. The journalist asked me the questions that any inquiring non-programmer might have when considering all these wacky languages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Why do we need new programming languages? Why are there so many of them? Why isn’t there a single standard language that all programmers use?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Facebook announced &lt;a href=&quot;http://hacklang.org/&quot;&gt;Hack&lt;/a&gt; and Apple announced &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/swift/&quot;&gt;Swift&lt;/a&gt; earlier this year, those questions weren’t present in much of the reporting. If there’s one thing that’s changed in the time since Emerging Languages started, it’s a general perception that polyglotism is here to stay and that periodically learning new languages is part of being a well-rounded professional programmer. That open and exploratory attitude may not be universal, but it’s certainly more prevalent today, to the credit of the PLT community as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Go is a rejection of advances in PLT, Hack and Swift offer warm and welcoming embraces to denizens of the ivory tower. Hack infuses familiar PHP with many powerful features from Haskell, while Swift looks not at all unlike the hypothetical trimmed-down and edited Scala we’ve been promised. Both languages were met with curiosity and enthusiasm when announced. I find this thoroughly encouraging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of Emerging Languages is not solely to showcase the new languages with that will see wide adoption. Some writing is for writers, some music for musicians, and some programming languages are, in turn, for other programming language designers. What I’ve tried to facilitate is an open exchange of ideas; a cross-pollination between industry and academe, static and dynamic, functional and object-oriented, practical and whimsical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If nothing else, I hope that five years of Emerging Languages has answered the “whys” above while making a little more space in which we can explore the languages and tools that will carry the craft of programming into an uncertain and demanding future.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
   <author>
     <name>Alex Payne</name>
     <uri>https://al3x.net/about.html</uri>
   </author>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dear Marc Andreessen</title>
   <link href="https://al3x.net/2014/06/17/dear-marc-andreessen.html"/>
   <updated>2014-06-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://al3x.net/2014/06/17/dear-marc-andreessen</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;dear-marc-andreessen&quot;&gt;Dear Marc Andreessen&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pmarca&quot;&gt;Marc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up using your work. Thanks to one of my parents being employed by a university, I got to use Mosaic to browse the early Web way before most people had even heard of it. My first software development internship was a summer spent using beta versions of Netscape technologies – what was then “LiveScript” and “dynamic HTML” – to sketch new interface elements for a protean web collaboration app. I rooted for Netscape when Microsoft came barging in to the browser market. When you started &lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com&quot;&gt;A16Z&lt;/a&gt; a few years ago I was excited to see what you’d invest in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve got a big audience of admirers. I’ve counted myself amongst them, but lately you’ve made it a challenge. I just can’t square with the way of looking at our industry, political economy, and the future laid out in your &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.pmarca.com/2014/06/13/this-is-probably-a-good-time-to-say-that-i-dont-believe-robots-will-eat-all-the-jobs/&quot;&gt;latest post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You seem to think everyone’s worried about robots. But what everyone’s worried about is &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;, Marc. Not just you, but people like you. Robots aren’t at the levers of financial and political influence today, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oxfam.org/sites/www.oxfam.org/files/bp-working-for-few-political-capture-economic-inequality-200114-summ-en.pdf&quot;&gt;folks like you sure are&lt;/a&gt;. People are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pewglobal.org/2013/05/28/world-worried-about-inequality/&quot;&gt;scared&lt;/a&gt; of so much &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gallup.com/poll/166904/dissatisfied-income-wealth-distribution.aspx&quot;&gt;wealth&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.policymic.com/articles/70811/these-stunning-maps-prove-just-how-much-the-rich-control-u-s-politics&quot;&gt;control&lt;/a&gt; being in so few hands. Consequently, wherever you and other gatekeepers of capital direct your attention – towards robots, 3D printers, biotech, whatever – you’re going to detect a fearful response as people scramble to determine the impact of your decisions and whims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate is, as ever, really about power. So let’s set robots aside, and with them your black and white dichotomy of pro-growth, pro-tech heroes versus regressive Luddites. In our country, most people have &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nsf.gov/statistics/seind14/index.cfm/chapter-7/c7h.htm#s3&quot;&gt;positive sentiments about science and technology&lt;/a&gt; while simultaneously being &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gallup.com/poll/169289/jobs-government-economy-remain-top-problems.aspx&quot;&gt;concerned about unemployment&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t know who your anti-robot villain is, but it’s not regular folks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;citizen-consumer-in-neoliberal-tomorrowland&quot;&gt;Citizen Consumer In Neoliberal Tomorrowland&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You come out swinging in your post, quickly invoking no less than the ghost of Milton Friedman to claim the last two centuries as an unqualified win for capitalist progress. Amidst the fray, this jab struck me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“[A]dvocating for slowing technological change to preserve jobs equals advocating for the punishment of consumers, and stalling the march of quality of life improvements[.]”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could go back and forth all day on what exactly defines technological change – I &lt;a href=&quot;https://al3x.net/2012/05/08/what-is-and-is-not-a-technology-company.html&quot;&gt;certainly have before&lt;/a&gt;. But what labor wants is &lt;em&gt;self-determination&lt;/em&gt;, not a slowing of technological change. Taxi drivers &lt;a href=&quot;http://online.wsj.com/articles/londons-black-cab-drivers-protest-against-taxi-apps-1402499319&quot;&gt;protesting Uber &lt;/a&gt; aren’t saying that they want apps out of their cabs. They want leverage to negotiate wages and working conditions so they aren’t &lt;a href=&quot;http://justin-singer.org/blog/2014/06/beautiful-illusions/&quot;&gt;barely scraping by&lt;/a&gt;. The pushback is on exploitative business models, not technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Let markets work”, you say, “so that capital and labor can rapidly reallocate to create new fields and jobs.”  Well, we’re three decades into an era of systemic &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deregulation#By_country&quot;&gt;deregulation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.peri.umass.edu/fileadmin/pdf/programs/globalization/financialization/chapter1.pdf&quot;&gt;financialization&lt;/a&gt;. The result? &lt;a href=&quot;http://yaleglobal.yale.edu/special_report/728&quot;&gt;Global recession&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=47851&quot;&gt;lingering structural unemployment&lt;/a&gt;, and an &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capital_accumulation#New_developments_in_capital_accumulation&quot;&gt;accumulation of capital&lt;/a&gt; at the top of the economic pyramid. In this climate, capital has indeed “rapidly reallocated” … into &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.economist.com/news/briefing/21590353-ever-more-wealth-being-parked-fancy-storage-facilities-some-customers-they-are&quot;&gt;hard-to-tax, hard-to-regulate asset classes&lt;/a&gt; like fine art. &lt;a href=&quot;http://wapo.st/170DygD&quot;&gt;Small business loans&lt;/a&gt; are still crunched and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2013/09/austerity-reinhart-rogoff-stimulus-debt-ceiling?page=1&quot;&gt;austerity reigns&lt;/a&gt; while &lt;a href=&quot;http://ctj.org/ctjreports/2014/06/offshore_shell_games_2014.php&quot;&gt;tens of billions in corporate profits sit in off-shore tax shelters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “severe macroeconomic down cycle, the credit crisis, deleveraging, and the liquidity trap” that you mention in passing? We “let markets work”, and that’s what we got in return. It’s been a failed experiment for everyone but the 1%. Dismissing “the crisis of inequality” as just a “pessimistic economic theory” has not been, historically, a move that’s gone well for aristocracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-means-of-production&quot;&gt;The Means of Production&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I didn’t jibe with your take on recent macroeconomic history, I was heartened to see that you’re interested in empowering individuals through technology:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[T]he current technology revolution has put the means of production within everyone’s grasp. It comes in the form of the smartphone (and tablet and PC) with a mobile broadband connection to the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we’re gonna throw around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/glossary/terms/m/e.htm&quot;&gt;Marxist terminology&lt;/a&gt;, though, can we at least keep Karl’s ideas intact? Workers prosper when they &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; the means of production. The factory owner gets rich. The line worker, not so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owning a smartphone is &lt;a href=&quot;http://tedcurran.net/2013/04/09/own-the-means-of-production-what-karl-marx-knew-about-opportunity-in-the-digital-economy/&quot;&gt;not the equivalent of owning a factory&lt;/a&gt;. I paid for my iPhone in full, but Apple owns the software that runs on it, the patents on the hardware inside it, and the exclusive right to the marketplace of applications for it. If  I want to participate in their marketplace, Apple can arbitrarily &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imore.com/tag/rejected-apps&quot;&gt;reject my application&lt;/a&gt;, extract whatever cut of my sales they see fit, and change the terms whenever they like. Same story with their scant competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed like a lot of people were going to get rich in the “app economy”. Outside of Apple and Google, it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/11/18/business/as-boom-lures-app-creators-tough-part-is-making-a-living.html?pagewanted=all&quot;&gt;turns out&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://motherboard.vice.com/blog/that-amazing-app-you-thought-of-wont-make-you-rich&quot;&gt;not so much&lt;/a&gt;. For every WhatsApp there are thousands of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/2014/04/no-exit/&quot;&gt;failures&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real money in tech is in platforms, network effects, &lt;em&gt;scale&lt;/em&gt;. Sell pickaxes and jeans to the miners, right? Only today it’s Amazon selling the pickaxes. The startup with its servers on EC2 is about as likely to find gold as a ’49er panhandler. Before the startup goes out of business, Amazon gets paid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thehill.com/opinion/mark-mellman/196054-mark-s-mellman-the-end-of-the-investor-class&quot;&gt;shrinking in number&lt;/a&gt; but growing in wealth and &lt;a href=&quot;http://talkingpointsmemo.com/dc/princeton-scholar-demise-of-democracy-america-tpm-interview&quot;&gt;political influence&lt;/a&gt;, own the means of digital production. Everyone else is doing shift work and hoping they still have jobs tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You spent a lot of paragraphs on back-of-the-napkin economics describing the coming Awesome Robot Future, addressing the hypotheticals. What you left out was the essential question: &lt;em&gt;who owns the robots?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;robots-and-safety-nets&quot;&gt;Robots and Safety Nets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure we all get by in Awesome Robot Future, you think we should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Create and sustain a vigorous social safety net so that people are not stranded and unable to provide for their families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes! Absolutely. With you one hundred percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The loop closes as rapid technological productivity improvement and resulting economic growth make it easy to pay for the safety net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You lost me again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, technology that enhances productivity can make products and services cheaper. Emerging technologies can also create demand for things that are inherently expensive – cutting-edge medical procedures and treatments, for example – driving up costs in entire economic sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless we collectively &lt;em&gt;choose to pay for a safety net&lt;/em&gt;, technology alone isn’t going to make it happen. Though technological progress has sped up over recent decades of capitalist expansion, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=47944&quot;&gt;most people on the planet are in need of a safety net today&lt;/a&gt;. The market hasn’t been there to catch them. Why is this different in Awesome Robot Future? Did I miss one of Asimov’s Laws that says androids are always programmed to be more socially-minded than neoliberals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate that smart, ambitious people like you are thinking about a future of universal prosperity. You borrow  terminology from finance in saying that you’re “way long human creativity”. While I’m creeped out by the commodification of our species’s ingenuity, I appreciate the sentiment. If our industry stops painting anyone who questions our business models as Luddites and finds creative ways to build products and services that sustainably address real needs, maybe we can hold on to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2014/06/23/140623fa_fact_lepore?currentPage=all&quot;&gt;receding myth of triumphal disruption&lt;/a&gt;. Hopefully we can agree that there are many more meaningful quality of life improvements technology has yet to deliver on before we can start brainstorming the “luxury goods markets” of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, we don’t need to wait until a hypercapitalist techno-utopia emerges to do right by our struggling neighbors. We could make the choice to pay for  universal health care, higher education, and a basic income tomorrow. Instead, you’re kicking the can down the road and hoping the can will turn into a robot with a market solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to everyone who offered feedback on drafts of this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
   <author>
     <name>Alex Payne</name>
     <uri>https://al3x.net/about.html</uri>
   </author>
 </entry>
 
</feed>
